<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Global Health Engineering</title>
<link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Homepage for slides, tutorials, and other teaching material.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.549</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Motivation for Team Award</title>
  <dc:creator>Lars Schöbitz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2024-02-27-swissrn-award/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This motivation was written in response to the call for nominations for the Swiss Reproducibility Award 2024. The motivation was written by Lars Schöbitz, a team member at the Global Health Engineering group at ETH Zurich.</p>
<p>The result of the review process was announced on 8th May 2024 and this nomination has not been selected as the winner of the category.</p>
<section id="motivation-word-count-347350-words" class="level1">
<h1>Motivation (word count: 347/350 words)</h1>
<p>We are dedicated to rigorous, transparent, and reproducible research. We aim to make all our research outputs reproducible and foster an Open Science culture. For this purpose, we use public GitHub repositories for version control, collaboration, and integration with Zenodo for long-term archiving and generation of a Digital Object Identifier (DOI).</p>
<p>We categorize our data into three stages:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stage 1: unprocessed raw data</li>
<li>Stage 2: processed analysis-ready data</li>
<li>Stage 3: data supporting publication results</li>
</ul>
<p>The raw data’s value is relatively low, but the code transforming it into analysis-ready data is invaluable. This code enhances transparency, promotes reusability, and boosts efficiency. It streamlines data cleaning, a crucial but often overlooked task. Moreover, by packaging our code as functions, we enhance efficiency in data cleaning for similar future projects. We ensure a complete audit trail from raw to analysis-ready data by openly sharing both alongside the code within the same repository. In addition, we use a permissive CC-BY license, assign DOIs, and link ORCID IDs to acknowledge all contributors, including those often unrecognized in scientific outputs (e.g.&nbsp;surveyors and lab technicians). Finally, our data is published as an R data package, enhancing accessibility and usability.</p>
<p>In Stage 2, we use the above R data package to prepare a reproducible manuscript. We utilize a literate programming tool to integrate narrative and code. The manuscript is stored and managed in another git repository. It receives a separate DOI, highlighting the differences between data cleaning and curation activities, which is performed by a data steward supporting the group, and the actual work that goes into authoring a manuscript, fine-tuning tables, figures and models, which rests with the scientists.</p>
<p>In Stage 3, we produce CSV files for the data supporting the publication results (e.g.&nbsp;tables, figures, models), allowing others to use our results quickly.</p>
<p>Our team has an Open Science Specialist who mentors our staff and students in applying open science principles, which unifies our team, aligning everyone with our vision and mission. Our team deserves this award to recognize our efforts to make science more rigorous, transparent, and reproducible.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2024-02-27-swissrn-award/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Attention, Prof: You need a data steward for your team.</title>
  <dc:creator>Lars Schöbitz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2024-02-13-data-steward/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Note:</strong> This blog post was published is a re-published version from the <a href="https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news/2024/02/blog-attention-prof-you-need-a-data-steward-for-your-team.html">Global Health Engineering website</a>. For attribution, please see the <a href="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/3-blog/posts/2024-02-13-data-steward/#citation">Citation information</a> at the end of this post.</p>
<section id="lead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lead">Lead</h2>
<p>You are a professor. You’re working long hours; you’re working weekends; you’re sitting in committees, and stuck in meetings that could have been emails; you’re teaching, grading, supervising, and mentoring. And now, on top of all that, you are supposed to make all your research data public, by applying FAIR principles. You need a data steward.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-a-data-steward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-a-data-steward">What’s a data steward?</h2>
<p>In simple terms and in the context of research, a data stewards are defined as “people who support the management of research data and reproducible data workflows in research groups, institutes and departments.”<sup>1</sup></p>
</section>
<section id="what-profile-do-they-need" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-profile-do-they-need">What profile do they need?</h2>
<p>Few established programmes specifically qualify people to be a data steward (e.g.&nbsp;Postgraduate Center University of Vienna2). At the moment, it’s a skill that’s mostly learned on the job. Do not look for academic degrees (e.g.&nbsp;a PhD) or for someone on an academic career path (e.g.&nbsp;with a long list of publications). Look for someone who has an affinity for IT, has worked in various organizations (government, private sector, research) , and with different types of data (lab experiments, observations, quantitative &amp; qualitative surveys). A Research Software Engineer, which is a more established term, could be a good fit, but there are other suitable profiles, too.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-can-you-offer-them" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-can-you-offer-them">What can you offer them?</h2>
<p>Whether it’s data stewardship or research software engineering, both career paths still need to be fully recognized and established within the scientific community. However, at ETH Zurich, there is an attractive career path for someone without a PhD. It falls under the “administrative, technical, IT and laboratory staff” category. The assigned function code 4042 (System specialist / software engineering) offers an attractive salary for someone with &gt;5 years of experience, the yearly appraisal interview for mechanisms of a performance-bound annual increase, and also the potential for a permanent position.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-the-tasks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-the-tasks">What are the tasks?</h2>
<p>A data steward will support you in defining your strategy for Research Data Management (RDM). Ideally, this is a strategy that promotes the concepts of open research data and open code to support computational reproducibility, a practice that is increasingly important to make research more rigorous, transparent, and impactful. When we established our group in 2021, we defined this role more generally as “Open Science Specialist”, and you can find the published job description<sup>2</sup> for your own use. Since then, we have established new projects and defined our RDM strategy and workflows<sup>3</sup>.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-a-data-steward-supports-the-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-a-data-steward-supports-the-group">How a data steward supports the group</h2>
<p>On a group level, a data steward hosts strategic meetings. They organize workshops to identify current file and data management practices within a group. They don’t prescribe one way of doing things but rather help determine the best practices for the group, allowing individual researchers to use the workflows and tools that suit them best to maintain scientific autonomy.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-a-data-steward-supports-the-individual" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-a-data-steward-supports-the-individual">How a data steward supports the individual</h2>
<p>On an individual level, a data steward offers weekly RDM support. They become the bridge from abstract concepts like FAIR principles, version control, and literate programming to the actual intellectual work needed.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-stewardship-in-practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-stewardship-in-practice">Data stewardship in practice</h2>
<p>At Global Health Engineering, we aim to make all our research outputs reproducible and foster an Open Science culture. In our workflow (which starts with designing a research study and ends with the production of a scientific article), we categorize our data into three stages:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stage 1: unprocessed raw data</li>
<li>Stage 2: processed analysis-ready data</li>
<li>Stage 3: data supporting publication results</li>
</ul>
<p>The unique work required to manage the collected data is recognized in each of these stages. We assign a digital object identifier (DOI) to the code that transforms the unprocessed raw data from Stage 1 into processed analysis-ready data (Stage 2). Together, they form a data package, which is fully documented with relevant metadata, and is citeable and reusable by the research community. A data steward is uniquely positioned to support data cleaning and curation, so that the researcher can focus on applying their expertise to the data rather than on the data itself. The actual work that goes into authoring a manuscript, fine-tuning tables, and preparing figures and models rests with the researcher and is what we consider getting data from Stage 2 to Stage 3. The data steward remains available to support the researcher in applying best practices for data management. Still, the researcher is the one who is responsible for the analysis, discussion, and conclusions.</p>
</section>
<section id="eth-library-data-stewardship-network" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="eth-library-data-stewardship-network">ETH Library Data Stewardship Network</h2>
<p>The ETH Library initiated a programme funded by swissuniversities to build a data stewardship network at ETH<sup>4</sup>. It has identified six people at ETH who already consider themselves to have this role and dedicate 20% of their time to data stewardship activities beyond the tasks they already perform for the research group. Through these activities, data stewards can further explore and develop their skills and competencies in data stewardship and, at the same time, support other researchers in applying best practices for data management and sharing<sup>5</sup>.</p>
</section>
<section id="hire-now-discuss" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hire-now-discuss">Hire now &amp; discuss</h2>
<p>Hiring a data steward for your group who can connect and engage with other data stewards at ETH and beyond will significantly advance the impact of your research. If you are interested in speaking about hiring a data steward, please get in touch: &lt;ghe@mavt.ethz.ch&gt; or connect with us for a discussion on our open room on Matrix chat: <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#ghe-open:staffchat.ethz.ch" class="uri">https://matrix.to/#/#ghe-open:staffchat.ethz.ch</a></p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://library.ethz.ch/en/researching-and-publishing/data-management-and-policies/research-data-management/data-stewardship.html" class="uri">https://library.ethz.ch/en/researching-and-publishing/data-management-and-policies/research-data-management/data-stewardship.html</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><a href="https://github.com/Global-Health-Engineering/job-descriptions/blob/main/open-science-specialist/README.md" class="uri">https://github.com/Global-Health-Engineering/job-descriptions/blob/main/open-science-specialist/README.md</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p><a href="https://ghe.ethz.ch/open-science.html" class="uri">https://ghe.ethz.ch/open-science.html</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p><a href="https://library.ethz.ch/en/researching-and-publishing/data-management-and-policies/research-data-management/data-stewardship.html" class="uri">https://library.ethz.ch/en/researching-and-publishing/data-management-and-policies/research-data-management/data-stewardship.html</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p><a href="https://ethz.ch/staffnet/en/news-and-events/internal-news/archive/2023/03/interview-eine-vision-fuer-open-science-and-data-stewardship-an-der-eth-zuerich.html" class="uri">https://ethz.ch/staffnet/en/news-and-events/internal-news/archive/2023/03/interview-eine-vision-fuer-open-science-and-data-stewardship-an-der-eth-zuerich.html</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{schöbitz2024,
  author = {Schöbitz, Lars},
  title = {Attention, {Prof:} {You} Need a Data Steward for Your Team.},
  date = {2024-02-13},
  url = {https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news.html},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.8318442},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-schöbitz2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Schöbitz, Lars. 2024. <span>“Attention, Prof: You Need a Data Steward
for Your Team.”</span> <em>Global Health Engineering Blog</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>open science</category>
  <category>open data</category>
  <category>metrics</category>
  <guid>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2024-02-13-data-steward/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2024-02-13-data-steward/dalle-overworked-prof.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>We can’t decolonize research until we fix publishing</title>
  <dc:creator>Elizabeth Tilley</dc:creator>
  <link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-11-14-change-publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Note:</strong> This blog post was published is a re-published version from the <a href="https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news/2023/11/blog-we-cant-decolonize-research-until-we-fix-publishing.html">Global Health Engineering website</a>. For attribution, please see the <a href="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/3-blog/posts/2023-11-14-change-publishin/#citation">Citation information</a> at the end of this post.</p>
<p>In the olden days, back before the internet, academic publishing was a laborious, but distinguished process. Authors would submit manuscripts to prestigious publishers, who would in turn, seek out the most renowned scientists in the field and solicit their commentary. The publisher would then type-set, print, and mail the bound paper journal to the few institutions that could afford the pricey, yet vital, subscription. Being an invited reviewer, or an editor was an honour, and the honour was deemed to be sufficient compensation for hours, if not days of work.</p>
<p>But things changed. On the one hand, “open-access” publishing has allowed millions (billions?) of people to read scientific papers without having to pay for a subscription; as of 2020, about 36% of articles have full open access <sup>1</sup>. In 2021, The International Water Association (IWA), which publishes important WASH-sector journals like Water Science &amp; Technology<sup>2</sup>, and my favourite, WASHDEV<sup>3</sup>, announced that 10 of their titles would be published completely open-access<sup>4</sup> going forward and would allow authors from 103 countries to publish for free, or for an unlucky 33, a 50% discount<sup>5</sup> (sorry, Nicaragua). These initiatives are part of “decolonizing research”, i.e.&nbsp;increasing access to those researchers and students without the means to subscribe, submit, or read papers behind unaffordable paywalls. Unfortunately, researchers from the Global South, are still publishing at rates far lower than their more funded colleagues, and even more worrisome, are still rarely included as authors about work done in their own countries: of the publications on Africa climate research, 58% (7232) included no African authors<sup>6</sup>. The measures in place are not enough, but there is growing recognition that more must be done to increase diversity and reduce bias within publishing, and fee waivers are a start.</p>
<p>On the other hand, for-profit publishing houses have become increasingly commercial and monopolistic, multiplying the mechanisms for making money from authors while expanding the need for unpaid reviewers and editors. Currently, academic publishing is dominated by 5 main houses: Elsevier, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Taylor &amp; Francis, Springer Nature, and SAGE who, combined, generate about 50% of the $19 billion in annual profit<sup>7</sup>. Elsevier, who manages 2928 different journals, reported £8.5 billion in revenue for 2022, and £2.6 billion in adjusted operating profit<sup>8</sup>. Meanwhile, few editors are paid for their service, and the hoards of reviewers, upon whom the entire industry rests, are kindly thanked (sometimes with a coupon).</p>
<p>As a response to what can only be called the greedy hyperaccumulation of wealth, some are pushing back. More than 40 scientists resigned from the editorial board of Elsevier’s journal <em>Neuroimage</em><sup>9</sup> and in 2019, The University of California (one of the largest academic institutions in the US) decided to not renew its $11 million a year subscription fee<sup>10</sup> contract with Elsevier, after lengthy negotiations failed to ensure that all UC publications would be made open access. These bold actions are commendable and are adding cracks to an already eroded foundation of trust in traditional publishing. Transformation is underway and inevitable but requires action from everyone: not just big account holders. What, you may be wondering, can I do? Whether you are a first time reviewer or a seasoned pro, I’ve compiled a few, simple actions that you can take to help make publishing more fair, diverse, and efficient for everyone.</p>
<p><strong>Actions for Reviewers who want to make an impact within the current system</strong></p>
<p>In 2022, over 5 million papers were published<sup>11</sup>. For any given paper, an Editor may send out between 5 and 20 reviewer invitations to get 2-3 acceptable reviews that can be returned to, and actually help, the author. Editors don’t want to flood your inboxes with requests, but we are increasingly becoming desperate to find sufficient and suitable reviewers within a manageable time frame. The best thing you can do as a reviewer is to accept the invitation, write a great report, and submit it on time. This keeps the wheels of academia moving.</p>
<p>If you don’t have the time or expertise, the next best thing you can do is reject the invitation immediately. Typically, an editor will set a “respond-by” date: if the invited reviewer does not respond within say, 2 weeks, the editor will look for another. Waiting until the invitation expires means that the clock starts again, and the paper continues to languish, frustrating the author and editor alike. If you really can’t do the review, click the “reject” button and let the Editor get to work on finding a replacement.</p>
<p>However, before blindly following my advice and rejecting every invitation that comes your way, consider your obligations to the system as well as your opportunities to change it. Go check your profile on Web of Science<sup>12</sup>: there, you can see your publications, your citations, and your review statistics. With a Peer Review to Publication ratio of 1.9:1, I am in the 95th percentile of reviewers who have a median of 0.3:1. In other words, I review almost 2 papers for every one I publish, which is at the low-end of what is needed to fully cover the reviews that I receive for my publications. For everyone else who is reviewing less than 1 paper for every 3 they publish, we need more from you. And if you haven’t been invited as a reviewer yet, send an email to the editor of your favourite journal asking them to add you to their database: they will be thrilled!</p>
<p>And yes, asking for more is a big request; especially for junior faculty, women, and those already burdened with various types of unpaid labour. But you have choices: consider passing up requests from “top tier” journals and focus your limited time on providing feedback for first-time authors or manuscripts from less represented countries<sup>13</sup>. As long as the journal is indexed<sup>14</sup>, you get the same amount of credit for reviewing for a journal that is considered “less prestigious”, but your impact will be much greater. Importantly, you can also always decline to review if you see something you don’t like: refusing to take on a manuscript without an author from the country of study, sends a strong signal to the editor, and hopefully, in time, the journal.</p>
<p>Until we have a complete overhaul of the publishing industry that includes new models of reviewing<sup>15</sup>, funding<sup>16</sup>, and disseminating research<sup>17</sup>, we must do our best to exist within it. However, small, consistent, acts by millions of ethical academics will hasten the crumbling of a system that excludes too many and profits too few. What role will you play?</p>
<p>Elizabeth Tilley is currently an Associate Editor for WASHDEV<sup>18</sup> and WaterSA<sup>19</sup>, and was formerly an Editor for Waste Management<sup>20</sup> and The Malawi Medical Journal<sup>21</sup>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>https://wordsrated.com/academic-publishing-statistics/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>https://iwaponline.com/wst↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>https://iwaponline.com/washdev↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>https://iwa-network.org/news/iwap-open-access/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>https://iwaponline.com/open_access/pages/Research4Life↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2021.10.023↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>https://wordsrated.com/academic-publishers-statistics/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>https://stories.relx.com/2022-relx-highlights/index.html↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>https://t.co/0aamG7bemJ↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>https://www.universityofcalifornia.edu/news/why-uc-split-publishing-giant-elsevier↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>https://wordsrated.com/academic-publishing-statistics/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn12"><p>https://www.webofscience.com↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn13"><p>https://www.ajol.info/index.php/ajol↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn14"><p>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3354504/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn15"><p>https://openreview.net/about↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn16"><p>https://doi.org/10.1186/s41073-021-00118-2↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn17"><p>https://zenodo.org/records/7974116↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn18"><p>https://iwaponline.com/washdev↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn19"><p>https://watersa.net/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn20"><p>https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/waste-management↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn21"><p>https://www.mmj.mw/↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{tilley2023,
  author = {Tilley, Elizabeth},
  title = {We Can’t Decolonize Research Until We Fix Publishing},
  date = {2023-11-14},
  url = {https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news.html},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.8318442},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-tilley2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Tilley, Elizabeth. 2023. <span>“We Can’t Decolonize Research Until We
Fix Publishing.”</span> <em>Global Health Engineering Blog</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>decolonization</category>
  <category>publishing</category>
  <category>peer-review</category>
  <guid>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-11-14-change-publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-11-14-change-publishing/dalle-scientific-article.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creating collaboration on the ground: Reflecting on my first visit to Kenya</title>
  <dc:creator>Jakub Tkaczuk</dc:creator>
  <link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-10-10-collaboration-kenya/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Note:</strong> This blog post was published is a re-published version from the <a href="https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news/2023/10/blog-creating-collaboration-on-the-ground-reflecting-on-my-first-visit-to-kenya.html">Global Health Engineering website</a>. For attribution, please see the <a href="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/3-blog/posts/2023-10-10-collaboration-kenya/#citation">Citation information</a> at the end of this post.</p>
<p>As a freshly employed senior scientist at Global Health Engineering, part of my role is coordinating the multitude of student projects we offer each semester. Our students are engaged in a range of vital research projects related to human health across several African countries. For instance, over the past two years GHE students have partnered with Sistema Bio in Kenya to design and test the use of biogas for the thermal disinfection of wastewater. And, although as a mechanical engineer I have been able to evaluate and advise on this work, one problem remains - I have never been to Kenya and I’ve never personally engaged with the problems we are trying to help address. What’s the best way to address this professional shortcoming? Although we are all trying to reduce our personal carbon emissions, Zoom calls can only get you so far - sometimes you have to travel to learn.</p>
<p>In September 2023 I had the privilege to travel to Kenya with my supervisor Prof.&nbsp;Tilley to connect with our biogas project partners. My journey in Kenya allowed me to engage with a variety of individuals from diverse backgrounds who all enriched my own understanding of Kenya and its socio-​technical challenges. This included learners and educators at schools in Kiababu and Ikinu, a Meru University of Science and Technology professor<sup>1</sup>, and entrepreneurs in Kisumu<sup>2</sup> made. The enthusiasm of students and educators was contagious; I was impressed by their dedication to learning. Apart from all the engaging and meaningful exchanges, I also stirred cubic meters of human waste for the first time in my life. Again, Zoom is a useful tool, but standing together and getting your hands dirty trying to solve a problem can bring the answer much quicker. With all of the partners in the same space, learning together, we were able to identify issues with the biogas installation, found clear paths for further development, and devised a sustainable plan for future collaboration to scale up our findings nationally.</p>
<p>By accident, at the same time as our stay in Kenya, the first Africa Climate Summit<sup>3</sup> took place, bringing around 30 - 35 thousand visitors to Nairobi. I had a chance to exchange with the Summit’s participants. The opportunity was invaluable and provided additional context for framing my work. After the Covid-​19 pandemic, everyone got used to virtual meetings and remote working, but the trip reminded me that travel, and the experiences that come with it, can be invaluable. Although you may collaborate from a distance, in-​person interactions can provide immediate answers to problems which otherwise would take long days to understand through a chain of email exchanges. In retrospect, my first trip to Kenya was a rich and diverse experience, both professionally and personally. I departed with an intent to return, and a clearer vision of how I can support both my students and our Kenyan partners. Moreover, I left Kenya with a profound sense of appreciation for its culture, as well as hope for its future to be brighter. Although I may have returned to Zurich, to a calendar full of online meetings, I’m already thinking ahead to my next trip.<br>
</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://www.must.ac.ke/celebrating-excellence-dr-joy-riungu-receives-the-distinguished-alumni-award-2022-from-ihe-delft/" class="uri">https://www.must.ac.ke/celebrating-excellence-dr-joy-riungu-receives-the-distinguished-alumni-award-2022-from-ihe-delft/</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><a href="https://www.opero-services.com/" class="uri">https://www.opero-services.com/</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p><a href="https://africaclimatesummit.org/" class="uri">https://africaclimatesummit.org/</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{tkaczuk2023,
  author = {Tkaczuk, Jakub},
  title = {Creating Collaboration on the Ground: {Reflecting} on My
    First Visit to {Kenya}},
  date = {2023-10-10},
  url = {https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news.html},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.8318442},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-tkaczuk2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Tkaczuk, Jakub. 2023. <span>“Creating Collaboration on the Ground:
Reflecting on My First Visit to Kenya.”</span> <em>Global Health
Engineering Blog</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>collaboration</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-10-10-collaboration-kenya/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-10-10-collaboration-kenya/biogas-digesters-drawing.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In an era of open science, how is ‘transparency’ shifting within qualitative research</title>
  <dc:creator>Marc Kalina</dc:creator>
  <link>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-09-04-qualitative-data/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Note:</strong> This blog post was published is a re-published version from the <a href="https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news/2023/09/in-an-era-of-open-science-how-is-transparency-shifting-within-qualitative-research.html">Global Health Engineering website</a>. For attribution, please see the <a href="https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/3-blog/posts/2023-09-04-qualitative-data/#citation">Citation information</a> at the end of this post.</p>
<p>Qualitative research is inherently not reproducible or replicable, a fact those with a more positivist view of knowledge creation find hard to digest. Reproducibility means obtaining consistent results using the same protocol and data, while replicability entails obtaining the same results using the same methods but with different data or a different sample. When using interpretive qualitative methods (which rely on the co-creation of knowledge between researcher and respondent), both the study conditions and the results obtained can hinge on a variety of factors, not least of all, the positionality of the individual researcher. Simply put: when you ask someone a question, you are not guaranteed the same response I might receive.</p>
<p>Therefore, within qualitative research it is more common to speak of transparency, rather than reproducibility or replicability, when evaluating the scientific rigour of a given piece of work. And, while the broader scientific community has moved towards increased openness with data and analysis, there has been a growing debate within qualitative research communities on how much transparency is necessary or possible within current praxis. Sebastian Karcher<sup>1</sup> of the <a href="https://qdr.syr.edu/">Qualitative Data Repository</a> has helpfully distinguished between three three types of transparency most relevant in qualitative research.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Production transparency:</strong> Information on how a study generates or collects data. This can include an interview schedule, and the types of methodological detail that would flesh out a good methods section, such as sample, subject recruitment, exclusion criteria, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Analytic transparency:</strong> Information on how data is prepared and analysed.</li>
<li><strong>Data access:</strong> Data availability, including access conditions.</li>
</ol>
<p>Of these forms, the first two have become increasingly <em>de rigueur</em>, with detailed methods sections becoming expected, and information on analysis, including codebooks, becoming increasingly common as supplementary submissions to articles. However, data transparency, including open use and access for qualitative material, especially within the social sciences, has lagged far behind other disciplines where open access is increasingly becoming the standard. There are practical reasons for this, because, as Sebastian Karcher notes, transparency within qualitative research is not a straightforward path, and is often fraught with ethical considerations and practical barriers. What are we doing at Global Health Engineering (GHE) to move this discussion forward and become more transparent in our own work?</p>
<p>At GHE we have made a pledge to embrace the full spectrum of transparency: to make all of our data, either quantitative or qualitative, open access under permissive licenses, and to publicly document how it has been produced and analysed<sup>2</sup>. This is, of course, important, so that the rigour of our research practice can be clearly evaluated, and so that our data can be accessible to other researchers, who may favour other modes of analysis, allowing the words of our respondents to resonate further and make an impact beyond what we may have foreseen.</p>
<p>Through our partnership with the <a href="https://openwashdata.org/">openwashdata</a> team we recently published <a href="https://openwashdata.github.io/biogasoutcomesmalawi/">our first open access qualitative dataset</a>: a series of 61 semi-structured interviews with biogas plant owners in southern Malawi <span class="citation" data-cites="schobitz2023biogasoutcomesmalawia">(Schöbitz et al. 2023)</span>. Moving forward, we intend to publish all of our work in similar fashion, but as a qualitative researcher going through this process for the first time, what did I learn from the experience?</p>
<p>First, making our data open access necessitates a change in ethical practice, particularly in how we obtain consent and inform participants on how their responses will be utilised. Will participants be as willing to speak freely if they know their responses will be made public, albeit anonymously? Second, the preparation of qualitative material for open access is an important step– but is time and resource intensive. Even with an in-house ETH data steward who was able to automate some of these processes, the anonymisation and packaging of transcripts is time consuming. Although we were able to devote the time and resources towards publishing the data package, I am concerned about the feasibility for scholars in less-resourced institutional contexts of giving their work the same platform as standards for transparency shift.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, we are pleased with the results of our first effort, and invite engagement and feedback from the greater scientific community. Moving forward, what do we want to improve? First, we would like to be more timely with our outputs, with data packages being published soon after they are collected, ensuring their broader usefulness and to support our own published analyses. Second, to date, we have only published transcripts in English. In the future we will also publish transcripts in the language in which the data collection was conducted, so that the un-translated voices of our respondents can stand on their own. Finally, we intend to develop data management guidelines and open source tools to support data preparation processes so that scholars from low-resource contexts can pursue data publishing without regard to material constraints.</p>
<p>The future is hard to predict, but we are hopeful it will be more transparent.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-schobitz2023biogasoutcomesmalawia" class="csl-entry">
Schöbitz, Lars, Sebastian Camilo Loos, Marc Kalina, Jonathan Olal Ogwang, Jonathan Kwangulero, and Elizabeth Tilley. 2023. <span>“Biogasoutcomesmalawi: <span>Data</span> for 61 Semi-Structured Interviews with Biogas Owners in <span>Malawi</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8289621">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8289621</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is a great blog post by Open Working summing up a presentation by Sebastian Karcher at TU Delft on the limits of reproducibility within qualitative research: <a href="https://openworking.wordpress.com/2019/02/11/what-does-reproducibility-mean-for-qualitative-research/" class="uri">https://openworking.wordpress.com/2019/02/11/what-does-reproducibility-mean-for-qualitative-research/</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Learn more about how we do this in this interview with Dr.&nbsp;Julian Dederke of the ETH Library: https://ethz.ch/staffnet/en/news-and-events/internal-news/archive/2023/03/interview-eine-vision-fuer-open-science-and-data-stewardship-an-der-eth-zuerich.html↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{kalina2023,
  author = {Kalina, Marc},
  title = {In an Era of Open Science, How Is “Transparency” Shifting
    Within Qualitative Research},
  date = {2023-06-21},
  url = {https://ghe.ethz.ch/ghe-blog-news.html},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.8318442},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-kalina2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Kalina, Marc. 2023. <span>“In an Era of Open Science, How Is
<span>‘Transparency’</span> Shifting Within Qualitative
Research.”</span> <em>Global Health Engineering Blog</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8318442</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>qualitative data</category>
  <category>transparency</category>
  <category>transcripts</category>
  <guid>https://global-health-engineering.github.io/website/blog/posts/2023-09-04-qualitative-data/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
